## Education

2018 - 2023 University of California San Diego, CA.

PhD Candidate, Electrical and Computer Engineering, GPA: 4.0

Advisor: Prof. Dinesh Bharadia

2016 - 2018 New York University, Tandon School of Engineering, NY.

MS, Electrical and Computer Engineering, GPA: 3.96

Advisor: Prof. Shiv Panwar

2012 - 2016 Indian Institute of Technology (IIT Kanpur), India.

Bachelors of Technology (B.Tech.), Electrical Engineering, GPA: 9.5 (out of 10)

## Research Statement

My research aims to innovate wireless networks by taking a multi-faceted approach to optimization. I focus on not only enhancing throughput, but also addressing crucial factors such as reliability, low latency, security, and ease of deployment in real-world scenarios.

# Research Experience

Aug 2022- Sustainable Multi-user Millimeter-Wave systems, with Prof. Dinesh Bharadia.

Ongoing • Developing a multi-user beam management and sensing scheme to ensure link reliability, avoid interference and guarantee high per-user throughput with power-efficient mmWave systems.

Aug 2021— **Securing mmWave automotive radars**, with Prof. Dinesh Bharadia & Prof. Aanjhan Ranganathan.

Aug 2022 • Developed a spoofing attack mechanism targeting automotive radar systems, capable of causing sensor malfunction.

o Designed and built a spoofing device using a mmWave reflect-array and commercially available components.

Aug 2021— [Infocom'23] Flexible and low latency multi-user mmWave, with Prof. Dinesh Bharadia.

Aug 2022 • Discovered a vulnerability in current mmWave systems, which limits their ability to perform frequency multiplexing for multiple users due to the directional beam only being able to illuminate one user direction at a time.

• Designed a new power-efficient front-end architecture that can split the frequency bands into multiple concurrent directions, enabling flexible frequency multiplexing, low latency, and higher spectrum utilization.

Aug 2018– [Sigcomm'21] Reliable mmWave Links using Multi-beamforming, with Prof. Dinesh Bharadia.

Aug 2021 • Developed beam management scheme that ensures multiple diverse paths are available to mmWave devices to maintain 100% reliable packet transfer even under random and unpredictable link blockage events.

 $\circ$  Prototyped a 5G standard-compliant mmWave network using USRP X310/X410 and off-the-shelf phased arrays and demonstrated the effectiveness of our scheme.

Jul 2018- Wireless Virtual Reality, with Prof. Dinesh Bharadia, Prof. Pamela Cosman.

Aug 2021 O Developed a viewport-aware Truncated Square Pyramid (TSP) scheme for 3D to 2D transformation of 360° videos.

• Analysed trade-off between video quality and bandwidth and developed algorithms to tune a truncation parameter for optimal performance.

Jan-June [MS Thesis] Millimeter Wave Blockage Analysis, with Prof. Shivendra Panwar.

2018 • Analyzed the impact of occlusions by mobile blockers on mmWave link reliability in an outdoor mmWave environment with macro-diversity (connectivity with multiple base stations).

• Our results indicate that the minimum density of BS required to satisfy the QoS for URLLC applications is mainly driven by reliability and latency constraints rather than coverage or capacity requirements.

## Selected Publications

Hotmobile **IK Jain**, RR Vennam, D Bharadia, "Delay Phased Arrays: Towards programmable beam-bandwidth for 5G poster 2023 networks", *HotMobile poster 2023*.

Infocom 2023 **IK Jain**, RR Vennam, R Subbaraman, D Bharadia, "mmFlexible: Flexible Directional Frequency Multiplexing for Multi-user mmWave Networks", *IEEE Infocom 2023*.

IEEE S&P RR Vennam, **IK Jain**, K Bansal, J Orozco, P Shukla, A Ranganathan, D Bharadia, "Spoofing Attacks on

2023 Automotive Radars using Millimeter-wave Reflect Array", IEEE Security and Privacy S&P 2023.

- WPMC 2022 T Qiu, **IK Jain**, R Wu, P Cosman, D Bharadia, "Delivering 360-degree video with Viewport-adaptive Truncation", *International Symposium on Wireless Personal Multimedia Communications (WPMC) 2022.* 
  - HotCarbon A Gupta, **IK Jain**, D Bharadia "Multiple smaller base stations are greener than a single powerful one: 2022 Densification of Wireless Cellular Networks.", *ACM HotCarbon Workshop 2022*.
    - Sigcomm **IK Jain**, R Subbaraman, D Bharadia "Two beams are better than one: Towards Reliable and High 2021 Throughput mmWave Links", *ACM SIGCOMM 2021*.
- mmNets 2020 **IK Jain**, R Subbaraman, TH Sadarahalli, X Shao, H Lin, D Bharadia, "mMobile: Building a mmWave Testbed to Evaluate and Address Mobility Effects", 4th ACM Workshop on Millimeter-Wave Networks and Sensing Systems (Mobicom Workshop mmNets), 2020.
  - NSDI 2020 R Ayyalasomayajula, A Arun, C Wu, S Rajagopalan, S Ganesaraman, A Seetharaman, **IK Jain**, D Bharadia, "LocAP: Autonomous Millimeter Accurate Mapping of WiFi Infrastructure", *Usenix NSDI*, 2020.
  - MDPI 2019 A Choromanska, **IK Jain**, "Extreme Multiclass Classification Criteria", vol 7, issue 1, *MDPI Computation Journal*, 2019.
  - JSAC 2018 **IK Jain**, R Kumar, S Panwar, "The Impact of Mobile Blockers on Millimeter Wave Cellular Systems", *IEEE Journal on selected areas in communications (JSAC)*, 2018.
    - ITC 2018 **IK Jain**, R Kumar, S Panwar, "Driven by Capacity or Blockage? A Millimeter-wave Blockage Analysis", *IEEE International Teletraffic Congress (ITC30), invited paper*, 2018.

## Patents

- US Patent **IK Jain**, et al., inventors. A platform for xApp development with RAN intelligent controller. *Patent* (provisional) *pending, contact VMware*
- US Patent D Bharadia, **IK Jain**, R Subbaraman, T Sadarahalli, inventors. Enabling Reliable Mmwave Link Using (provisional) Multi-Beam Pro-Active Tracking. *Patent pending, contact UC San Diego (innovation@ucsd.edu)* 
  - US Patent D Bharadia, R Ayyalasomayajula, A Arun, C Wu, S Rajagopalan, S Ganesaraman, A Seetharaman, **IK Jain**, (granted) inventors. Enable Indoor Navigation with Context assisted Localization.

### Work Experience

- June-Sep VMware, Palo Alto, CA, USA.
  - 2022 Topic: VMWare RAN Intelligent Controller (RIC), Mentor: Dr. Rakesh Misra
    - Designed near-real-time applications (xApps) to improve wireless connectivity and reduce inter-cell interference in Open-RAN framework.
- June-Aug Nokia Bell Labs, Murray Hill, NJ, USA.
  - 2017 Topic: Millimeter Wave Beam Training Algorithm Design, Mentor: Dr. Özge Kaya
    - o Developed an adaptive beam training algorithm for mobile multi-user scenario in outdoor mmWave cellular networks.
    - o Achieved an average of over 60% reduction in beam-steering delay over a sequential search baseline.

## Teaching and Mentoring Experience

## Teaching Assistant.

- WI 2021,23 ECE 257B- Modern Wireless Communication (Graduate).
- Spring 2020 ECE 157B- Communication and Sensing Systems (Undergraduate) helped design a new class.
- Spring 2018 EEGY 9123- Introduction to Machine Learning (Graduate).
  - Fall 2017 EEUY 4563- Introduction to Machine Learning (Undergraduate).
- Spring 2017 ELGY 6373- Internet Architecture and Protocols Lab (Graduate).

**Mentorship**, I mentored two PhD students and 10+ BS/MS students at UC San Diego. I particularly help historically underrepresented and underprivileged students.

# Leadership

2021–2022 The Marconi Society, Scholar in Residence.

Served as a student scholar for facilitating the Marconi Society meetings with the chair Vint Cerf and other prominent scientists, engineers, and policymakers.

2021–2022 Escribamos Ciencia K12 team, UC San Diego.

Developed interesting science modules and videos for K12 students on topics such as electricity, internet, nuclear power, etc., under guidance of Prof. Olivia Graeve.

2020-2022 Coordinator, Jacobs Undergraduate Mentorship Program, UC San Diego.

Mentored underprivileged students through lab tours, industry talks, panel discussions, technical workshops, etc., and bridged the communication gap between undergraduates and graduate students.

2020–2021 **O.W.L Reading group**, *Inter-continental collaboration*.

Founded in Fall 2020 as a small group of Ph.D. students interested in research talks and discussion on recent conference papers and has grown over 100+ members in a year.

2019–2021 Vice President, ECE graduate student council, UC San Diego.

Responsible for providing communication between ECE students and the ECE department and organizing weekly events such as seminars and coffee hours.

#### Services

#### 2019–2022 Technical Reviews.

IEEE Trans. Vehicular Technology (TVT) 2019-20 National Conference on Communications (India) 2021

IEEE Globecom 2021

**IEEE WCNC 2022** 

IEEE Access 2021-22

IEEE SPAWC 2022

2021 Technical Program Committee (TPC).

ACM Mobicom S3 Workshop 2021

2021 Lead organizer and moderator.

Sigcomm'21 Social Trivia

2019 Artifact Evaluation Committee.

ACM CoNEXT 2019

### Awards and Honors

- Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship winner 2022-23.
- o Winner of 3-minute research talk competition at ACM Mobisys'20, Mobicom'21, Mobicom'22.
- o Commencement award for the best graduate student service in ECE, UC San Diego, May 2021.
- o Commencement award for the best MS Academic Achievement in ECE, at New York University, 2019.
- Commencement award (Motorola Gold Medalist) for the best all-round performance in Electrical Engineering, IIT Kanpur, May 2016.
- o Samuel Morse MS Fellowship (full financial support during MS at NYU) 2016–2018.
- o Secured All India Rank 390 (amongst 0.5 million students) in IIT-Joint Entrance Exam 2012.